agencies charge 10,000 or more for the
SEO audit checklist process I'm about to
show you. Just follow this process step
by step and you'll have a complete
battle plan for improving your rankings
in Google Chat GBT and everywhere your
customers are searching. I'm Nathan
Gotch and I've led hundreds of
successful SEO campaigns over the last
decade and have helped thousands of
businesses get predictable SEO results
through my SEO systems. So, let's get
right into it with number one, which is
find crawling and indexing
opportunities. So, there are two things
you need to do to get started with this
audit. Number one, you're going to need
a simple Google sheet. Now, I'm going to
be building this from scratch, but
normally I'd be using templates, which
are actually available inside of Gotcha
SEO Academy, but for the sake of doing
this, I'm going to show you how to do it
completely from scratch from N to end.
So, first get a Google sheet, and we're
going to create the first tab, which is
crawl, and then we're going to go over
to Screaming Frog. So, I highly
recommend investing in Screaming Frog. I
don't get any affiliate commission or
anything by making this recommendation.
I've just been using this tool for
probably about a decade now, and it's
really critical for this audit process.
So, I highly, highly recommend. There's
other ones out there, but this is the
one I prefer cuz it's just nice and raw
and does exactly what it needs to do.
Now, it's extremely powerful and so you
have to make sure that you set it up the
right way. So, we're going to go through
some real quick configuration, you know,
protocols here, and then we'll get into
kind of the more analysis, quantitative
analysis. Okay, first things first, go
to configuration. Okay, we're going to
go to crawl config up here. And a couple
of things I usually like to make this
very simple. I'll get rid of I'll
uncheck all the resource links. I'll
uncheck a lot of things that are just
going to put a heavy load when you do
this crawl. So, if you just want to
follow the settings that I have, this is
going to be the quickest crawl that you
can get and get the most bang for your
buck, right? Okay? because you don't
want to get lost in in all the little
minutia. Okay, so I would just do this
first. Now, next we're going to go to
extraction. Once again, follow the same
settings that I have. You can also
include structured data here, but I'm
going to be doing this for go.com. We
don't have a ton of structured data on
that site, so it's not really a concern
of mine, but if you're doing local or
you're doing ecom, it might make a lot
of sense to use the structured data
audit as well. Okay, limits, nothing to
do here. Rendering, all good. Advanced.
You can play with some settings here,
but I keep this pretty standard.
Preferences, once again, all pretty
standard. Now, go to content. Once
again, this is all standard. And then
for duplicates, I do enable near
duplicates. I do enable spell and
grammar check. And then for the
embeddings, I do enable all of these as
well. So, semantic similarity and low
relevance as well. Okay, so these are
important because this can help us, you
know, kind of do some deeper analysis.
So I won't get into it right now, but
for now just the settings. All right, so
that's the first part. Now what we want
to do is go into the API access and
there's four things, no a three minimum
that I would recommend. Number one is
Google Analytics 4. So go ahead and set
that up. Just click this little gear
icon and you need the API. It will just
you can go and log in. Google search
console, the same thing. Going to go and
log in as well. And then the page speed
insights as well. So that's another one
that's going to require an API. But
these three here are going to give you a
massive amount of data to work with. And
we're going to be able to make really
datadriven decisions. And if you want to
do anything more advanced, you can
certainly integrate some of the AI
platforms as well, but it's not really
entirely necessary really. You just need
these three to get a really good idea of
what's going on. So that is the setup.
Go ahead and get all this set up, get
all the APIs right, and then you're just
going to start that crawl, and then I'll
show you the next steps from here.
Number two, find internal linking
opportunities. So once the crawl is
complete, go ahead and export this
report and we're going to put it into a
Google sheet. But I would actually keep
this open because I'm going to be
showing you some other stuff later on in
this video where you can use Screaming
Frog to see some visualizations. Okay.
First, let's go over here to this
section. You can see I've already
imported the crawl. Okay. And first
thing I want to do is you want to find
internal linking opportunities because
in my opinion, when it comes to
technical SEO, internal linking is one
of the most powerful moves you can make.
So, what I like to do right away is go
ahead and freeze the top row, add a
filter, and then what we're going to do
is we're going to look at just indexable
content. And we'll go ahead and look at
this other stuff here coming soon. But
for now, we're going to scroll over and
immediately go to very, very important
columns when it comes to internal
linking. First is crawl depth. So, this
column right here, I'm going go and open
that up. And what we want to look at is
any page that is deeper than three
clicks. Okay? So, we're going to go down
here, and you can do conditional
formatting if you want to, you know, do
this quicker. If you've got a bigger
website, you'll probably need to do
that. But for a smaller website like
this one, we're just going to go ahead
and mark it like this. Okay. Then, what
we're going to do is, and by the way,
crawl depth is simply how many clicks
does it take to get to that URL. So, the
deeper it is into your website, the
worse it's going to be for crawling and
most importantly for indexing. And if
your page doesn't get indexed, you're
simply not going to rank. So it's really
one of the most important things that
you can do. All right. Unique in links
very important is the quantity of unique
pages that are linking to that page.
Okay. Internal links only. Okay. So for
me what I like to do is do a toz and any
page that has we'll say in this case
maybe less than three internal links
we're going to go ahead and mark it. But
you know for the sake of this argument
let's go ahead and mark anything less
than five. Okay less than five. So what
we're starting to see here is a trend
that we've got a lot of pages that are
already based on the data. We've got
tons of pages are buried deep into the
architecture and we've got a lot of
pages that do not have a lot of internal
link support. So that's typically a
symptom of a few things. Number one, we
just haven't gone through the process to
inject internal links on relevant pages.
And number two, it can sometimes be a
symptom that those pages don't have a
lot of topic support. And we'll be
talking more about that here in a
second. But this is one of the best
places to start because you can really
get a good look into some really quick
wins that you can attack. Number three,
find page loading speed opportunities.
All right, so now let's use this report
to go and find some page loading speed
opportunities. So go ahead and just
scroll over and you're going to go all
the way past here and we're going to
look specifically at this column here,
which is performance score. Okay, so
when you are running your crawl with
screwing frog, you can if you have it
enabled, it will give you tons of data
about loading speed. I don't think
that's particularly important. I think
you just like in the case of the audit,
we're just trying to identify the really
lowest performing opportunities. Okay,
so right here we're going to see that
based on the performance score to me,
anything that's below an 80 is something
I'm probably just going to go in and
mark. Okay? Because once you get to
about an 80 performance score, you're
going to be pretty good. The law of
diminishing returns will start to set
in. So, there's probably not going to be
much benefit beyond that. But all of
these are relatively low. Okay? So,
basically, nearly every page on the site
needs a lift as far as loading speed,
core web vital, whatever it may be.
Okay? And this is not because optimizing
for core web vitals is a direct ranking
factor. It's more of an indirect ranking
factor. Meaning, if a user gets to your
website and they're having a poor
experience, there's a high probability
that they're not going to stay there
long and they might bounce back to
Google, which is also known as pogo
sticking. They may have, you know,
produce really low engagement rate on
that page itself. So, all of those are
negative signals, but that's not all. On
top of it, we know that large language
models when they land on a site, they
give very, very little time. you have
probably less than 3 seconds for that
page to load before that, you know, that
crawler bounces. So, if you want to get
good performance on Google Chat, GBT and
AI search platforms, loading speed is
really, really critical. So, it's not
necessarily because it's a direct
ranking factor. It's more because it's
going to make your crawling and your
indexing better. And of course, it's
going to make user experience better,
which we know translates to better
conversions. So, there's no reason to
not do it. It's something that it should
absolutely be a priority because it is
one of those lead domino things that
affects so many different areas in your
campaign. So, I'll be showing you what
we can do to fix this. But for now, we
can just get a really highle overview.
And if we want, I'll show you a real
quick example of this. You if you
download the Lighthouse extension, it
might actually be native inside of
Google Chrome. But if you go in here and
then you do view page source, okay,
actually, we'll just do inspect. And
then we're going to do do this and we're
going to scroll over and you'll see here
lighthouse. Okay. Okay. And if you want
on a page by page basis, you can run
this. Okay. So, for example, we'll do
desktop since most of my traffic is
desktop. And then we'll just do this.
And what it's going to do, it's actually
going to on the spot analyze just this
one dedicated page. And if you do this
for 5 to 10 pages, you're going to get a
really good idea of the opportunities
that exists. Now, the good news is when
you fix one page as far as loading
speed, it typically impacts the whole
site as a whole. So it's not like you
need to go page by page and try to fix
these. Okay. So based on what we're
seeing here, this one is actually doing
really well on desktop. So not any
issues on that front. So what I would do
is I would actually run this on mobile
and see if mobile's the thing that's
causing a problem. Okay. So but just to
give you an idea, this is how quickly we
can see this and then we can start to
diagnose and fix this. Number four, find
404s and broken links. All right. So now
let's find some 404 errors. So, not
every 404 is bad. It's okay to have a
404 error if that was the actual intent.
Meaning, you wanted to delete that page
and you want Google to remove it from
the index. That is totally okay. Not all
404s are bad, but the 404s that are
actually bad are the ones that have
positive KPIs or that were accidental in
nature. Okay? So, scroll back over in
your crawl and you're going to look
under the status code column here and
make sure that for indexable, we're
going to go ahead and actually do
non-indexable. So, we're going to get a
good idea of these different status
codes that we can work with. So, but for
this one, we're just going to focus on
the 404 specifically. So, we're going to
click on this. And you can see we've got
a significant amount of 404s. We've got
about 53 404 pages. Okay. Now, a lot of
these are intentional. All right? A lot
of them are intentional, outdated
content, stuff that shouldn't be around
anymore. We just went ahead and deleted
it. However, what you want to do is you
want to scroll over all the way over
here. Then we're going to look to see if
these pages have KPIs. Okay. Now, what
I'm seeing here is a lot of these pages
do have KPIs. Okay. So, we have, you
know, actually every single one of the
404s with the exception of one has some
positive KPIs. Okay. So, pretty much all
of these are going to need some sort of
action here. Okay. So, we have almost
all of them have traffic. Most of them
have impressions in Google Search
Console. Some are even getting clicks.
Some are actually getting events as well
and the engagement rate is pretty decent
on some of these even though they're
404s now. So, this is not a good sign.
This is something that we need to go and
fix, right? So, we need to figure out
where can we send these 404 pages? Where
can we redirect these pages or how can
we improve these pages to recapture this
potential traffic and engagement? Okay?
Because based on what we're seeing here,
this is over the last year or so. We're
looking at 5 million impressions that
are now going to be lost basically to
zero. Like we're going to go to zero on
these pages because they're 404s if we
don't act on this now. So this is really
not a good thing. Number five, find thin
content. All right, so now we're going
to find some thin content. And so
there's lots of different ways to define
what thin content actually is. I would
argue that it's not just about word
count. You could technically have a page
that has a significant word count that
doesn't add anything new to the equation
that could be considered thin in my
opinion. However, for the sake of this
argument, we're just going to focus on
word count alone. So, go ahead and
scroll over and we're going to look at
the word count column. Now, for me to be
for a page to be considered low word
count, in my opinion, it has to
basically be below 500 words. So, if
it's below 500 words, it's going to get
flagged. Okay? This doesn't mean that
we're going to go and just add a bunch
of junk content on here. It just means
that now it's been flagged and now we're
going to put it into further
investigation. Okay, so that is it. It
doesn't mean we're going to act on it.
Doesn't mean we're going to actually go
and try to fix these pages necessarily,
but they are now in a little bucket
where now we can start to see what's
going on and see if there's an
opportunity to improve these pages,
possibly delete some of these pages,
whatever it may be. Number six, find
duplicate content. So for a page to be
considered duplicate, it means that it
has the same exact content on more than
one page. Okay? And this is obviously
not a good thing. We don't want to have
multiple pages with the same exact
content on our website. Now, if you did
the screaming frog crawl configuration
correctly, you can scroll over to the
right and you go to this little section
right here, which is closest near
duplicate match or number of near
duplicates. This is the amount of pages
that are basically exactly the same.
Now, in the case of Gotch SEO, there
aren't any. So, this is not showing up.
However, if you want to double check,
you want to make sure that there's not
any pages that are, you know, exactly
the same, go ahead and run a sighteliner
crawl. And you run a scri a sighteliner
crawl and then you go to duplicate
content. And anything that's below 30%
is probably not anything you need to be
concerned about. But, we do want to look
here and go ahead and sort this by match
percentage and see if there's any
alarming issues here. Now, we see that
there's, you know, pageionation going on
here from the blog. This is all stuff
you can ignore. Nothing to be concerned
about. But I'd be more concerned about
actual pages where there's a lot of
duplication. Okay? So, this one here
where there's like 32%. We want to see
where there is duplication occurring.
Okay? So, based on what we're seeing
here, there is some stuff that is
relatively similar across multiple
pages. So, this may be a situation where
we may want to consider making this a
little more unique than what it
currently is. It's not an exact match,
but it's very, very close to the point
where I would actually flag this page as
an opportunity to upgrade and improve.
Okay, so use Sideliner to your
advantage. Number seven, find keyword
cannibalization. So now we want to find
instances of keyword cannibalization,
which is when you have two pages that
are basically competing against each
other for the same exact keywords with
the same exact intent. Now, this is one
of the most confusing concepts for a lot
of people. So I'm going to try to make
this really, really clear. Okay? So I'm
going to show you an example of one that
you might think is keyword
cannibalization, but it isn't. Okay? I'm
going to show you an example of this. So
I'm going to go to rankability.com and
I'm going to show you how I do this.
on our website here. So an example is
like we go over here to the products and
we go to content optimizer. Okay. Now if
we look at the detailed Chrome
extension, you'll see that this is
optimized for best AI content
optimization tool for SEO. Okay. So
specifically best you know SEO content
optimization tool. So singular version
of that keyword. But then, as we just
did recently, we published a blog post
and we're actually going after, you
know, once again, best AI SEO content
optimization tools. Okay? So, some
people would think that those two pages
are going to compete with each other,
but they actually are not. And the
reason is because cannibalization isn't
just about the seed topic that you have
here. It's also about the intent of the
page and how it's structured. So, for
example, that previous one I showed has
commercial intent. It's talking about
our one tool that we have and we're
stating the benefits of using that tool
specifically on that page. It's a sales
page, right? It's a sales page. It's not
the same. This here is for someone who's
doing investigative research and trying
to come to a buying decision. They're
trying to figure out what is the best
tool that I should use. So, this is
different because this is helping. This
is a buyer's guide. Okay? It's very,
very different. Plus the commercial page
as I showed you before is a singular
variation here you know for the keyword.
So we're talking about one tool just one
tool and it's this one and this is the
one we're talking about. The other ones
are plural. Okay. So we're talking about
many different tools in this instance.
Okay. So very very different. This is
not keyword cannibalization. And in fact
this is exactly what you should be doing
pretty much in any SEO situation. You
can have your commercial page and then
you can have your, you know, buyer guide
with commercial intent/investigative
intent. Okay, those two things are not
going to compete with each other. In
fact, they actually tend to lift each
other up. It's quite cool when you see
it happen. Okay, now if we wanted to
find keyword cannibalization within our
crawl, it's actually really simple. So,
let's just pretend like I'm going to
find some in here. Now, more than
likely, we're not going to have keyword
cannibalization, but let's give you an
example of what I would do if I was
trying to find it. So I usually start
with the title. Okay. And let's say I
wanted to find keyword cannibalization
for SEO training specifically. Okay. So
we're going to run that through. We're
going to do text contains. We're just
going to look at SEO training. Okay. So
what we find here is a bunch of pages
that are all optimized for that one
seed, right? Just SEO training. But when
you look at these, none of these are
cannibalizing each other. Okay? Because
each of them is targeting a different
location. Some of them are targeting,
you know, kind of that the homepage has
more national intent, but none of these
are actually competing against each
other. Okay, that is the key. So, you
can still have that same seed in there
as long as there's other modifiers in
there to modify the intent, right? And
that's all that matters. So, you know,
if this was, let's say I did have
multiple pages about, you know, SEO
training in Baltimore, like let's say I
had two or three of those pages, then we
start to possibly cause some problems
and that's not going to probably produce
any positive outcomes. Okay? But as long
as the intent is different, as long as
it truly is a different page, then
you're probably not going to run into
keyword cannibalization. It's one of
those things where people really put way
too much emphasis on it. And I've seen
tons of websites that just don't care
about it at all and they do pretty well.
But I wouldn't recommend that. I would
still, you know, focus on one core topic
per page. And then the general rule of
thumb is if you want to create another
page, make sure that it has different
intent. Number eight, find irrelevant
content. All right, so now it's time to
find irrelevant content. So this is
really important because we want to make
sure that our topic authority and our
topic focus on our website is very, very
tight. We don't want to start venturing
off into topics where we don't have
subject matter expertise. And so, and on
top of it, it's also really, really hard
to build a really tight cluster, which
I'll be showing you here in a second.
But first, we want to identify this
content that's just totally off base.
Okay? So, there's a lot of ways we can
do this, but let's just make it really
simple. So, we know that obviously this
website's about SEO. So, what I'm going
to do is I'm going to look and I'm going
to search the title tags. Okay? So, text
does not contain can be a quite powerful
ally here. And I'm going to do SEO.
Okay? Because anything that doesn't have
SEO in it is probably a good candidate
to start investigating. Okay? So, when I
look at here, I can immediately start to
identify some irrelevant topics. So,
like this one here, which is best script
timer for 2025. Now, funny enough, this
page I built back in I think it was
maybe the beginning of 2023 because I
was actually showing people how to build
a free tool using Chat GBT. And this
thing still actually ranks pretty well,
but it isn't very closely related to the
core subject matter expertise that we
have on the site. So, this would be a
candidate likely for redirection, maybe
deleting, something like that. Okay? And
we can go down the list and kind of find
these ideas. So, this is what you want
to do though. You want to kind of go
through these and look for these
opportunities. We have another one here
that's about pocket alternatives. Once
again, this was an experiment that I ran
to show people how quickly they could
build a website using vibe coding. Okay?
And so I created this post so I could
help lift a test project that I created.
Now, once again, not very relevant. And
you can see it doesn't connect well to
the core topic really at all. Okay, so
these are the types of pages that you
want to start to be pretty ruthless
about. And if they have positive KPIs as
we can go over here and check, you have
to think about how can we try to
preserve some of these positive KPIs
that exist. Okay, so like this one here
has pretty significant amount of traffic
over the last year. Same with this one.
Okay, so you know, we could just totally
eradicate it and lose out on that
traffic or we try to figure out a way to
rework it to make it relevant. So
there's a lot of options. Number nine,
find weak clusters. All right, so now
what we want to do is identify weak
clusters. So a cluster is simply a group
of pages that are all around one
particular topic. So let's say at the
core of a cluster, we have content
optimization tools. We're going to have,
you know, various posts about
alternatives and reviews about various
tools that are all going to link back to
that one core center. And so we want to
find these really tight clusters, but we
also want to find these really weak
clusters. And you can usually improve
performance for SEO just by improving
the strength of a single cluster. So
I'll show you an example of this. So
let's look on Gotch SEO specifically and
look for an example of like a pretty
strong cluster. So if you look at like
you know SEO training for example, you
can see we've got a pretty significant
amount of pages that are on this core
topic. Okay? So around 20 pages give or
take. So I would say this is a a
moderately strong cluster. Okay? It's
not super strong, but it's pretty
decent. Okay, then I'll show you an
example on rankability of another of one
that I would consider a very strong
cluster. Okay, so we'll go over here and
we'll go to blog and we'll look at this
one here. Okay, this is an example of a
pillar post. This is a a listicle that's
obviously targeting the kind of
investigative intent for these AI search
rank tracking tools. But within this,
we've covered each of these tools that
exist, but on top of it, we've also
created individual reviews for each of
the brands that are in this cluster.
Okay? And we're building out
alternatives and a bunch of other
different versions of this. So, by the
end of this, this one pillar post will
have potentially 75 to 100 supporting
assets around it. Okay? So people do not
go that deep and you can get a huge
advantage over your competitors by going
a mile deep on these topics. So the best
thing to do is if you're seeing low
performance for a particular topic,
examine the support that you've built
around that topic. Number 10, find
content quality opportunities. So now
we're at a point where you're going to
have to start to analyze each individual
page on a qualitative basis. We're going
to let the data lead us to these pages,
but then you're actually going to have
to look at them and and really kind of
diagnose each individual page. And so,
the way that I'm going to do this as far
as content quality is I'm just going to
look at the metrics. The best place to
start and see what pages are not
performing particularly well from an
organic search perspective. So, we're
going to go over here and the best thing
to do is just filter by impressions
because impressions is directly from
Google Search Console. And so, we have a
very low number of impressions. it means
we're this page is not ranking for very
many keywords within the top 100. So
that's a very good place to start. And
so based on what we're seeing here, if
we just look at these, we'll just take
the top, you know, 10 to 15 pages here
and we'll just highlight them in yellow.
And we can go over here and see what are
the types of pages that tend to not
perform very well from an organic search
perspective on our website. Now, this
website is very unique because we have a
lot of alumni from Gotcha SEO Academy.
So, these are all alumni pages. And I'll
show you an example of, you know, Chris
Dryer. This is a dedicated page
specifically for Chris Dryer, who's the
founder of rankings.io. And it naturally
is not going to get that much traffic
because that's not really what it's
designed for, right? You can tell it's
just pretty simple. It kind of shows his
credentials and his certifications and
obviously a quick testimonial and that's
it. Okay. Now, if I wanted to, I could
certainly beef this page up a little bit
more, right? I could add a little meat
to this page. I can give a little bit of
a better bio about Chris. I could
interview Chris and put that transcript
on there. So, there's a lot of options
for adding a little bit of relevant meat
to this page, but at the end of the day,
you know, this isn't your traditional
SEO driven page. So, but this is these
are the types of pages you want to pay
attention to. And we just don't want
lowquality stuff. That's really what
matters. And that is what you should be
on the hunt for is find the stuff that's
just not worth keeping on the site
anymore. And typically if you find
pages, my general criteria is pretty
simple. If the page has no traffic, no
impressions, and it has no back links,
it's a pretty good sign that it really
shouldn't exist anymore. Okay? And that
like all of the signals are pointing
towards that page just generally not
performing well unless it's new. But if
it's an established page and it has all
of those, you know, the lack of metrics,
either A, you know, the strategy wasn't
good or B, you know, you're going have
to go back to the drawing board and kind
of reformulate a strategy or in most
cases just delete it and, you know, move
on. Okay, so we have to identify these
pages so we can keep our site very very
lean and not waste precious crawl
resources on pages that just didn't
work. Number 11, find onpage SEO
opportunities. Okay, so now you want to
look for just basic onpage SEO 101
opportunities. And so a couple key
things you want to look for on any page
that we're actually trying to drive
organic search traffic on is you want to
make sure that the keyword appears in
the title, the meta description, also in
the URL, and we want it to appear in the
H1 and the first sentence. So when we
look at this page, once again, this is
an alumni page, so it's not necessarily
really built for SEO performance, but it
doesn't mean we can't squeeze more out
of it if we don't want. So if we or if
we wanted to. So what I would do is to
squeeze more out of this is think about,
okay, you know, Graham, you know,
instead of just trying to rank for his
name, what else can we rank for? Can we
rank for his brand name? You know, what
else can we do to drive more organic
awareness? And so what I would show you
an example here of like proper onpage
SEO. Okay, so like this one here is just
and this is what I call bare minimum on
page SEO. Okay, so this is an example.
We've got the keyword in the title tag.
We've got the keyword in the metad
description, right? We've got the
keyword in the actual slug in the URL.
And when we go to the headings, we've
got it in that first H1. We've got a
variation in the H2, which is also a
good idea. And then we've got it also in
the first sentence. Okay. So, if you do
that, that's like 50% of onpage SEO. The
other part of this that's really
important is using NLP, natural language
processing, or sometimes also called
NLU, which is natural language
understanding, which is a subset of NLP.
And we want to use that technology to
our advantage to make sure that we're
covering the most relevant topics inside
of our content. This is literally proven
to work. So, I'm going to show you here
in a second how to do that. Number 12,
find content optimization opportunities.
All right, so now you're at a point
where you're going to want to start to
audit each individual page to see how
relevant it is. And typically what I'm
doing is I'm focusing obviously on the
pages that are not performing really
well. So an example of this is for this
page here targeting dashword
alternatives. So in SAS, this is a very
common type of content framework to use.
And so based on what we're seeing here
right now, we're sitting around number
six, give or take. So, we'll go ahead
and just run this through Rankability.
Very simply, we're going to put the
keyword in here. We're going to select
import URL content. Then, we're going to
put the URL in there and then just run
the optimizer. All right. As soon as the
report is done, go ahead and click
through and we're going to go ahead and
take a look at the opportunities that
exist. So, based on what I'm seeing here
is we already have some opportunities to
improve this content. And so you have to
keep in mind whenever you optimize a
piece of content sometimes at the time
it was well optimized but as it starts
to age as it starts to get older you
have new competitors that are coming up
which means the overall amount of topics
can change and it can change the whole
dynamic. So it is to a certain extent
I'd say within you know a year or so it
is worth revisiting assets and there's a
good chance that you're going to
potentially fall if you don't keep up
with this. So, an example of this is
right now, you know, we see the
competitors, the ones that are ahead of
us are pretty well optimized. And
obviously, you expect Dashword to be
number two because it's their brand.
They're probably going to do pretty well
for this keyword. But the other ones, at
least as of right now, are more relevant
than we are. Okay. So, if we want to
improve our performance here, it's as
simple as going in here and sorting this
by unused and making sure we're covering
all of these topics that we have not
covered in this content. Okay. Now, you
don't have to cover every single one. We
typically recommend getting within, you
know, the optimal range of about 73 or
whatever the optimal range is telling
you, but aside from that, once you get
there, you're pretty much good to go. We
don't typically recommend people going
up to 100. That just is usually very
very aggressive and not necessary, but
based on our experience, just a simple
reworking of content, a little refresh,
a little reoptimization usually gives a
nice lift of at least two, three,
sometimes even four spots. It is that
effective. So, especially when Google's
already telling you that you're doing,
you know, pretty decently for this
keyword, right? You already have a page
that's pretty relevant. It's doing what
it should for the most part. You just
need to kind of rework it and make it
more relevant. Number 13, find
lowhanging fruits. So, at this point,
you probably already have a lot of work
to do just from this preliminary audit.
But what you can also do is start to
look at your keyword footprint. This is
really, really important because there's
so many opportunities that people are
just sitting on and not even attacking,
including myself. Okay, so I want to
show you a quick example of this. So
what I would recommend doing is going
and clicking average position and then
we're going to go down here and you can
sort this based on a particular cluster.
So like if you want to add a filter, we
could just go ahead and sort this by we
could do like you know training for
example since it's kind of our core
thing. We'll put this in here and we're
going to see what pages are doing that
are doing pretty well but would have a
would need a nice lift to go a little
bit higher. So you sort this by
position. So we can see, you know, the
ones that are performing well obviously,
but we really want to look at the pages
that are from positions 2 to 15. Okay,
that's really the sweet spot where we
want to go after particular keywords,
particular pages. So based on this, we
see Houston SEO training. We'll go and
verify incognito and see what this looks
like. And we could be number one. So
like this is why it's good to verify
because this one, it would be wasted
effort for us to go in here and
reoptimize since we're already doing
well. Okay. So, let's go with one that's
maybe a little bit further down here in
the ranking. So, like this one here,
which is AI SEO training. We'll go ahead
and take a look and we'll see how we're
performing for this one. We're going to
go and scroll down and let's take a
look. It said we're around page two,
give or take. So, it looks like we're
actually not page three possibly. Okay.
So, at this point, if we're not even on
the first three pages for that keyword,
some work has to be done, right? So,
we're going to have to go and reoptimize
for this keyword depending on, you know,
what page was getting picked up. Could
be the homepage, could be an internal
page. We'd have to do further
investigation. But this is the type of
work you want to do because these
keywords that are sitting in this sweet
spot, it doesn't take a lot to lift
them. Typically, usually some
reoptimization with rankability, that's
the first move. Making sure the
content's obviously high quality and
then going through and looking for
internal linking opportunities, right?
Because what you can do is you can go
and like take one of these pages for
example. And so we could take, you know,
one of these that's not doing super
well. So like I don't know, Orlando SEO
training. We'll go ahead and grab this
URL. And then we can go back here into
this section and we'll actually sort
this to find it. Okay. So we're going to
go ahead and find that specific URL. And
then what we can do is go and see how
much internal link coverage does this
URL have. Okay. We're going to take a
look. So based on what we're seeing
here, crawl depth of 16. Remember, we
found this earlier. So, it's buried
super deep into the architecture and it
has very little internal links. So,
right away, I've already got two quick
wins that I could go and attack right
now to improve the performance of that
one page. Either create more content,
look for more internal linking
opportunities. There's a lot of things
that I can do right away. And then on
top of it, it's also loading incredibly
slowly for some reason. So, another
opportunity for us to improve. So, right
away, we've already got optimize it with
rankability to improve the relevance.
We've got driving more internal links to
it and we've got improving loading speed
just by those three actions alone.
You're it's almost impossible to not see
performance gains. If that doesn't get
you to number one for whatever keyword
you're looking at as a lowhanging fruit,
then the next obvious step is to drive
back links to that asset and the
supporting assets around it. Okay,
that's the next level. But for the most
part, you can get very, very far with
content optimization, internal links,
and more topic support. Those three
things are very, very powerful and
wildly underestimated. So, I would
highly recommend looking at this bucket
of keywords as like you're sitting on
gold. You should attack them right away.
Number 14, find clustering
opportunities. So, once you've
identified your lowhanging fruits, the
next group of keywords that I really
love to go after are what I call
clustering opportunities. So any keyword
that's from position 50 and beyond falls
into this bucket of a clustering
opportunity. Now one nuance here. If you
have a brand new page that you just
published, it's very common to perform,
you know, between 50 and 100 in the
rankings. Okay, that's totally fine.
Ignore those. But it's more about the
ones that are established that are not
doing very well. So once again, Google
Search Console, you go right in here.
You can sort by position and you can
obviously filter by a keyword that
matters to you. And then we're going to
go in here and we're going to look for
opportunities that clearly we're not
doing a good job for. Okay, that's
basically what this tells us is that
whatever page is being picked up that's,
you know, driving impressions here is
not that relevant, is not that good in
one way or another. Okay, so an example
of this is technical SEO training. Now,
I know our site very well. We don't have
a technical SEO training page. We don't
have a technical SEO training sales page
or anything. Now, we have technical SEO
training inside of Gotach SEO Academy,
but we don't have a dedicated landing
page for it. And this is really
important because what this tells me is
that there is actual search demand for
this, which means it's worth pursuing.
It's worth building a dedicated page. I
have the proof now. Okay. So, sometimes
you can look at these clustering
opportunities as a way to measure
demand. Okay? That's really, really
important. So once you've identified
that demand, go and build those
dedicated pages because you have the
proof. Very likely it's going to do very
well. Now the question is how would I do
this? Not much of a surprise here. I
take this keyword. I go into rankability
and I run it through specifically the
content optimizer and I'm going to grab
all the NLP keywords from this. Okay?
I'm going to I'm going to build a whole
list of NLP keywords and I'm going to
build an outline. Now you can do this
with AI inside the platform. But my
criteria for determining whether I'm
going to use AI or manual is based on
competition. So if it's lower
competition, I'll go basically fully AI.
If it's higher competition, in the case
of the SEO industry is much higher
competition, I'm typically going to, you
know, get do a little bit of more manual
work to attack that keyword. Okay. So an
example like this, I'll probably build
out a commercial page and I'll probably
use a lot of artificial intelligence for
that. Okay, but just to give you an
idea, this is where I always begin
because the most important ranking
factor in Google is relevance. There's
nothing more important than just getting
a relevant page other than actually
getting it indexed. But after it's
indexed, making sure that it's highly
relevant to the keyword you're
attacking. And this is a tool that you
can use to do that. Number 15, find
topic domination opportunities. So topic
domination is simply the process of
attacking a keyword or topic on your
website and then taking that same exact
topic and attacking it across other
platforms that Google is known to index
on the first page very well. And also
that chat GBT and other AI platforms are
known to use as a source of retrieval.
Okay. So you want to try to blanket as
many of these surfaces as possible to
greatly influence the AI generator
responses inside of chat GBT and the
other AI platforms, but also to cover
more surface area in traditional search
as well. So an example of this is what I
would do is I'd go into Google search
console and look at some keywords that
I'm doing really well for just from a
traditional SEO perspective. An example
of this would be SEO books. Okay, so we
could take this seed and this can be our
focus of topic domination. So we'll go
ahead and take a look and we're going to
go over here and we're going to look at
how we're doing for this keyword. Now,
as of right now, we only have one asset
that's popping up, which is our actual
book here, the SEO entrepreneur. Okay,
so that's good that this is popping up.
We've got one win here, but that's not
good enough. We're going to scroll down
here and we're going to go all past this
and we're going to try to find other
situations where we also have some
coverage. Now, it looks like this blog
are covered our uh book as well. Okay,
so we're actually covered right here.
That's also really good. Okay, so we've
got two coverages on the first page,
which is really, really good. But our
website, our actual page here is ranking
not really that great. So, we'd want to
focus here and push this page up much
further. Maybe needs a little bit of a
refresh, needs a little bit of love, and
we can push it back up towards the top.
Okay, so that would be focus number one.
Once that has been reoptimized and
improved, my next move is immediately
going to go to YouTube and I'm going to
see if we've published any content about
that particular topic. Okay. So, we're
going to go to YouTube and we're going
to take a look. So, we'll go to my
channel and we know YouTube is one of
the most powerful mechanisms for driving
performance inside of Google cuz Google
owns YouTube. So, we're going to go
here. We'll look at SEO book and see if
we have anything about that. And I have
one kind of book here or one short about
it, but I don't have a dedicated video
about SEO books in general. So, that's a
golden opportunity to attack that
keyword knowing that it's very likely to
perform inside of Google. Okay, we know
that that's typically what's going to
happen and it's a source of retrieval
for the AI platform. So, we can see here
we've got a block right here where we
could go and attack this keyword. This
is the process of topic domination. Then
what I'm going to do is I'm going to
start to examine the first page and say,
"Okay, what other stuff is getting
picked up here?" Well, I see Reddit's
getting picked up. So, I need to go here
and see is there an opportunity for us
to, you know, inject our book into this
thread. The answer is no because it's
archived. So, we can't do anything about
this, but we can keep tabs on future
threads that will come that may replace
this thread in the future. Okay. So, we
see we've got a bunch of other ones here
that maybe we could go and investigate
further. Once again, that's archived.
And this is also archived. So, we'd have
to just kind of keep a pulse on this.
But what we can do is we can take note
of the subreddit that tends to pop up
the most. It's the SEO subreddit. So, we
need to stay on top of this and and set
up alerts in case books plus SEO gets
mentioned inside of this subreddit so we
can jump on it and try to promote our
book, right? It's very, very important.
Okay. Then, we're going to go down here
and I'm going to look for any other
places where I might be able to score
some coverage. We already got coverage
here. So then we'd look here on search
engine journal and try to see if we
could pitch trying to get on this list
as well. Now this looks like all branded
stuff. We're probably not going to be
able to get on here. So you're going to
have to kind of vet some of these
opportunities. We've got hrefs here.
Once again, are we showing up in this
list? It doesn't appear. So it doesn't
appear that we're actually showing up on
this list as of right now. So we would
want to go and try to pitch our book to
be on this list. Okay, very simple as
that. and so on and so forth. This is
the process. And so you're looking at
the opportunities here and then you're
going and attacking those. That way you
can get as many rankings as possible on
the first page of Google. That's topic
domination. Number 16, find critical
citation opportunities. So one of the
most powerful things you can do right
now to influence the AI platforms is to
just reverse engineer the citations or
in other words reverse engineer the
sources of retrieval that the AI is
going to. So as you know I won't get
deep into it here when you go into a
platform like chat GBT and you ask a
question and it doesn't know the answer
based on its training data or its
training cutoff it uses rag to go and
retrieve the information. so it can
generate a an accurate response so it
doesn't have to hallucinate through this
process. And so what you should do is
based on whatever keyword or topic
you're going to go after, run that same
exact topic through all of these
different platforms. Now, what I
recommend doing is run it through
ChatGBT, run it through Perplexity, run
it through Claude, and then run it
through Grock. Okay? And the reason you
want to do that is because each of these
systems uses slightly different forms of
retrieval. And you want to try to get
kind of a cumulative look at all the
different citation opportunities. And
this is super simple. Okay, it's simple
to understand but not easy to implement.
I want to be very clear on this. But
what I like to do is I will run these
queries through and I will look for the
gaps. Okay, so I ran, you know, best SEO
books here and we go down here and I'm
going to go ahead and look at the
citations and see are we being mentioned
on these citations. Okay, and so I'm
going to go one by one and I'm going to
see which of these were being mentioned
on and which we are not being mentioned
on. Okay? And then the ones that we're
not, we're going to go and do outreach.
I'm going to repeat the same exact thing
on Perplexity. Okay? Look at all the
citations and find those where we're not
getting coverage. Okay? Same thing on
Claude. Okay, same exact thing. We can
go here, click on the citations once
again. Boom. We can see all the
different citations where we can get or
coverage. And once again on Grock. Okay,
you'll notice you're going to find a lot
of similar citations, but you are going
to find some unique gaps that maybe you
didn't see if you only ran it on Chad
GBT. So run it across all of them, and
that's going to give you the greatest
pool of opportunities. Number 17, find
your competitor's top performing pages.
While you can certainly go in chat GBT
or an AI platform and help it generate
content ideas for you, it's never going
to be as good as actually going and
finding content ideas that have
quantifiable proof that they're actually
a good idea to build upon. The good news
is if you have some competitors that
have had some levels of SEO success or
even content success, you can go and see
the types of frameworks or templates
that they've used and you can produce a
you know use that same template to build
something unique knowing that it it has
a pretty high probability of working.
Okay, so go into HFS or Semrush, you
know, your tool of choice and then go to
Best Buy links. Okay. And you put your
competitor in here. And what we want to
do is we want to see the types of pages
that are proven to attract links. Now,
I'm looking at exploding topics here,
and there's clearly a trend. Okay? You
can start to see the commonality among
the pages that tend to attract a lot of
links. It just so happens to be
statistics driven pages. Okay? And once
you find a framework that's already
proven to actually attract these links,
you want to repeat that over and over as
they have done very intelligently. Okay?
And so we know that this works. We know
statistics are a very powerful technique
for linkbait, but it is going to be
different based on the industry that
you're in, but you can look at an
industry that is not yours and you can
find templates and then apply those in
your industry. And sometimes your
competitors have never done that and
you'll get a huge advantage there. So,
you know, deploying the same exact
strategy that's already been done a
million times in a particular industry
may not work as well. So, it's really
advantageous to transfer these ideas to
different industries and you might get
more bang for your buck. Number 18, find
misinformation about your brand. So, I
could dedicate an entire video to
cleaning up and auditing your brand for
consistency and accuracy, but just for a
very quick thing that you can do today
is you can probe Chat GBT's internal
training data to see what it knows about
your brand. Okay? So, and this is
actually completely free to do. So you
can just go into chat GBT and go to the
GPT section and then search generative
engine optimization. Okay, search that
and you're going to find free GPT that I
built a couple of months ago and it's
going to look like this. And all you
have to do is just go in here and enter
your brand name. But more importantly, I
would if it's a brand that's not like
really well-known like Nike for example
or Disney, then maybe add a little bit
of clarification in there so it can go
through the the neural network and try
to, you know, look in its training its
base training data to see more detail
about the brand itself. You need to add
maybe a little bit of context, but just
for the sake of argument, we'll just do,
you know, Disney like this. Okay, so
we're going to run Disney. And this is
built to only look at the at the core
training data. So, I do not have web
search enabled for this, and that's by
design. We do not want it to go to web
search. We just want to probe GPT5's
training data. Okay, that's all we're
trying to look for. So, this gives us
just a rough ballpark idea of, you know,
how what at least what chat GBT knows
about this brand to a certain extent.
Keep in mind, this is not a perfect
science. Some of this could be
hallucinated. If it doesn't know, it
might just make it up because of course,
it's not relying on web search. And when
it doesn't rely on web search, it can be
a little more inaccurate. So just keep
that in mind. It's not going to be
perfect, but it can at least give you a
ballpark idea and help you see like,
okay, doesn't look like, you know, chatb
knows a whole lot about our brand. So we
need to go and and take the necessary
actions to improve